{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "A shipment of arms to this group aboard the Eksund was intercepted by the French and discovered to have been sent by Muammar Gaddafi. Bobby Sands died in a hunger strike protesting the prison rights afforded to members of this group, which began to disarm after Sinn Fein [shin fayn] signed the Good Friday Accords with Tony Blair. For ten points, name this paramilitary group that split off from an “Official” nonviolent group shortly after “The Troubles” began in Ireland.",
      "answer": "Provisional Irish Republican Army or PIRA"
    },
    {
      "question": "This event’s end was hastened by the intervention of George Snowden’s militia, despite William McCleary’s numerous attempts at peaceful negotiation. Alexander Berkman’s attempt to assassinate a participant in this event brought it into the national spotlight. A group attempting to stop this event was caught while traveling in barges up the Ohio River. Pinkerton agents working for Henry Clay Frick failed to break, for ten points, what 1892 strike of Pennsylvania steelworkers at a Carnegie plant?",
      "answer": "Homestead Steel strike"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man wrote an analysis of the German psyche after World War II titled Anti-Semite and Jew. This first editor of the journal Modern Times popularized the phrase “existence precedes essence” in his Existentialism and Humanism, which rejected deterministic excuses for behavior. This philosopher popularized the idea that there are “two modes of consciousness,” and that “bad faith” forces human beings to adopt false values, in his Being and Nothingness. For ten points, name this French post-war philosopher and Nobel Laureate who was married to Simone de Beauvoir.",
      "answer": "Jean-Paul Sartre"
    },
    {
      "question": "A member of this family was targeted by the Soviet-backed Yanan Faction in the “Second Arduous March.” This family is honored on the “Day of the Sun.” A member of this family instituted the “Juche” [joo-chay] policy of self-reliance and took the title of “Eternal President,” while another member of this family allegedly ordered a hacking of Sony after he was unfavorably depicted in The Interview. Il-Sung, Jong-Il, and Jong-Un are members of, for ten points, what family that rules North Korea?",
      "answer": "Kim family"
    },
    {
      "question": "Thisscientistdiscoveredthatstereoisomersoftartaricacidrotatepolarizedlightinoppositedirections. He saved the silk industry in his country by determining that silkworms were dying from an infectious disease called flacherie. This scientist was able to save Joseph Meister from a dog bite due to his research into a vaccine for rabies. For ten points, name this French scientist whose namesake process removes harmful microorganisms from milk.",
      "answer": "Louis Pasteur"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man wrote that “If [...] bad men can be got rid of only by killing, then the killing must be done,” leading some to claim he was an accessory to the murder of William McKinley. This man’s ranch on an “Enchanted Hill” in San Simeon, California, includes a massive castle open to public tours. This mogul inspired Charles Foster Kane in Orson Welles’ 1941 film Citizen Kane. For ten points, name this early 20th century American newspaper publisher whose New York Journal rivaled the New York World of Joseph Pulitzer.",
      "answer": "William Randolph Hearst"
    },
    {
      "question": "Major cities in this country were seized by Yahya Khan’s troops during Operation Searchlight in an attempt to prevent the Awami League from taking power. In 1971, George Harrison organized the world’s first benefit concert to support this country, which was suffering a genocide during its war of independence from Pakistan. For ten points, name this country, now an independent country with capital Dhaka.",
      "answer": [
        "Bangladesh",
        "Concert for Bangladesh"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "As a result of this treaty, Portugal regained Colonia do Sacramento in Uruguay. This treaty forced North American tribes formerly loyal to France to open trade with all nations. Britain increased its hold on the slave market when it was given the asiento, along with Gibraltar, in this treaty. Philip, duke of Anjou, renounced his claim to the French throne as a result of, for ten points, what treaty that ended the War of the Spanish Succession?",
      "answer": "Treaty of Utrecht"
    },
    {
      "question": "This river was the subject of the Pick-Sloan plan, which sought to build the Garrison and Fort Peck Dams. Fort Mandan was built along the banks of this river as a wintering spot for a 1804-1805 expedition; that expedition, led by Lewis and Clark, traversed the entire length of this river, which flows past Omaha and Kansas City. For ten points, name this longest tributary of the Mississippi River, which joins it north of St. Louis.",
      "answer": "Missouri River"
    },
    {
      "question": "The instigators of this battle intended to start the assault shortly after the delivery of the Fourteen Part Message. A pilot who crash landed during this battle received support and animosity from the local populace in the Niihau Incident. Wheeler Air Field was repeatedly targeted in this battle, which controversially did not include a third wave of striking aircraft. For ten points, name this 1941 battle in which the USS Arizona was sunk.",
      "answer": "Battle of Pearl Harbor"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The losing side of this war used an encirclement technique called motti. The winners of this war were able to lease a naval base at Hanko and occupy the city of Vyborg. Its victors suffered heavy losses due to the effects of the Great Purge. The losers were forced to cede Karelia after the fall of the Mannerheim Line, despite the use of ski troops. The Continuation War followed, for ten points, what conflict between Finland and the Soviet Union, simultaneous with the start of World War II?",
        "answer": "Winter War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Finnish troops in the Winter War developed a makeshift anti-tank weapon named for this man, the Soviet foreign minister.",
        "answer": [
          "Vyacheslav Molotov",
          "Molotov cocktails"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country controls an archipelago with capital Funchal that is known for a variety of fortified wine. This country’s second-largest city sits at the mouth of the Douro River and lends its name to another fortified wine. This country transferred control of its Macau colony to China in 1999. Porto and the Madeiras are found in this nation, which is largely coextensive with the Roman province of Lusitania. For ten points, name this country with capital at Lisbon, which shares the Iberian Peninsula with Spain.",
        "answer": "Portugal or Portuguese Republic"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In addition to the Madeiras, Portugal also controls this other Atlantic archipelago, including the islands of Santa Maria and Terceira. It was discovered in an expedition sponsored by Henry the Navigator.",
        "answer": "Azores"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A man nicknamed after this animal, Charles Jones, worked with Charles Goodnight in a conservation effort to preserve their numbers. Another man nicknamed for this animal called his rifle Lucretia Borgia and once killed over sixty of these animals in an eight-hour hunting competition. The 10th Cavalry bore a nickname referencing this animal, a term eventually applied to several African-American regiments. William Cody’s nickname was that of, for ten points, what animal, whose population plummeted as American settlers traveled west?",
        "answer": [
          "buffalo",
          "bison",
          "Buffalo Bill",
          "Buffalo Soldiers"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Buffalo Bill’s Wild West Show included this man, at times a U.S. marshal and at times a vigilante, who was murdered while holding the Dead Man’s Hand at a poker game in Deadwood, South Dakota.",
        "answer": "”Wild Bill” Hickok or James Butler Hickok"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This party launched the Chakrabarti Inquiry after several of its own members made anti-Semitic statements. CCTV footage showed this party’s leader walking past available train seats in order to show that rail privatization has led to a shortage of space. Owen Smith lost this party’s 2016 leadership election, triggered after a vote of no confidence following Brexit. For ten points, name this party led by Jeremy Corbyn, the current opposition party in the British House of Commons.",
        "answer": "Labour Party of the United Kingdom"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Owen Smith received support for the Labour leadership from this former leader of the Labour Party. He stepped down after the Tories won the 2015 general elections.",
        "answer": "Ed Miliband"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Aspartofthisevent,theMeirokushasocietypromoted“civilizationandenlightenment.”Lawsenacted during this period included tax reform that returned land to the government and the replacement of the han system with prefectures. A group of reforms during this period were outlined in the Charter Oath. In this period, a group of daimyo fought the Boshin War against the government, and the Satsuma Rebellion was launched by discontented samurai. For ten points, name this period of 19th century modernization in Japan in which the emperor was restored to power.",
        "answer": [
          "Meiji Restoration",
          "equivalents for restoration",
          "descriptions of the Meiji era",
          "government"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Meiji Restoration began after the appearance of these colorful objects, led by Commodore Matthew Perry, which forced Japan to sign the Convention of Kanagawa.",
        "answer": "the black ships or the kurofune"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man began his “New Course” by appointing Leo von Caprivi as chancellor. He flew into a rage during an interview with the Daily Telegraph and sent the gunboat Panther to start the Agadir Crisis. This man replaced Helmuth von Moltke the Younger with Erich von Falkenhayn after the failure of the Schlieffen Plan. This grandson of Victoria supported Austria after the death of Franz Ferdinand and dismissed Otto von Bismarck. For ten points, name this last Kaiser of Germany, who ruled during World War I.",
        "answer": "Wilhelm II or William II"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Wilhelm II appointed this man Chief of the General Staff in the second half of World War I. He later served as president of the Weimar Republic.",
        "answer": "Paul von Hindenburg"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This character says “It is always better / to avenge dear ones than to indulge in mourning” to a grieving friend after the death of a man whose name translates as “ash army.” This character once lost a week-long swimming contest to his friend Breca. This man, who dies in combat with a dragon, is the subject of a poem that was translated by Seamus Heaney. For ten points, name this hero who kills Grendel and Grendel’s mother in an Old English epic poem.",
        "answer": "Beowulf"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This author claimed that the value of Beowulf as poetry, rather than as a historical document, had been overlooked in the English literary tradition in his lecture Beowulf: The Monsters and the Critics.",
        "answer": "J.R.R. Tolkien or John Ronald Reuen Tolkien"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man briefly suspended one campaign on Larry King Live. This man’s running mate asked “Who am I? Why am I here?” in a vice-presidential debate. Admiral James Stockdale ran with this founder of Electronic Data Systems, who used charts to advocate for a balanced budget and briefly led both George H.W. Bush and Bill Clinton in polling. For ten points, name this Texas businessman who founded the Reform Party and won nineteen percent of the popular vote in the 1992 election.",
        "answer": "Henry Ross Perot"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Ross Perot argued against what 1990s international political agreement, claiming it would create a “giant sucking sound?”",
        "answer": "NAFTA or North American Free Trade Agreement"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Constitutional Amendments",
      "prompt": "Which Constitutional amendment...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Protects freedoms of speech and exercise of religion?",
          "answer": "1st Amendment"
        },
        {
          "question": "Protects against cruel and unusual punishment, but not the death penalty?",
          "answer": "8th Amendment"
        },
        {
          "question": "Includes the Due Process Clause and Citizenship Clause and was passed during Reconstruction?",
          "answer": "14th Amendment"
        },
        {
          "question": "Responded to Vietnam War criticism by lowering the voting age?",
          "answer": "26th Amendment"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was inspired by Franklin Roosevelt’s unprecedented fourth electoral victory?",
          "answer": "22nd Amendment number is required"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the subject of D.C. vs. Heller and McDonald v. Chicago this century?",
          "answer": "2nd Amendment"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was revived by student Gregory Watson in 1982, then ratified in 1992? Description or number acceptable.",
          "answer": [
            "27th Amendment",
            "descriptions of “delaying Congressional pay raises until after the next election”",
            "“Congresspeople can’t give themselves raises”"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Ended a process that was defended in Federalist Paper No. 62 as a “double advantage” linking state and federal governments? Description or number acceptable.",
          "answer": [
            "17th Amendment",
            "descriptions of “requiring direct election of Senators”"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Robert Walpole",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Position, the head of the British government, that Walpole was the first to hold in 1721.",
          "answer": [
            "Prime Minister",
            "PM"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Name shared by the two British monarchs served by Walpole, the first two to take the name.",
          "answer": "George I and/or II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Prominent tower where Walpole was imprisoned by his political enemies.",
          "answer": "Tower of London"
        },
        {
          "question": "Residence that Walpole bequeathed to his political successors.",
          "answer": "10 Downing Street"
        },
        {
          "question": "Political party to which Walpole belonged. They opposed the Tories and the concept of absolute monarchy.",
          "answer": "Whig Party"
        },
        {
          "question": "Position held by Walpole as a junior minister, equivalent to America’s Secretary of the Treasury.",
          "answer": "Chancellor of the Exchequer"
        },
        {
          "question": "Credit bubble that occurred during Walpole’s rule, as a joint-stock company for trade in South America crashed.",
          "answer": "South Sea Bubble"
        },
        {
          "question": "Political subdivision that elected Walpole to Parliament. Walpole’s was a “pocket” kind, where he controlled over half the voters in the subdivision.",
          "answer": "pocket borough"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "North Africa in World War II",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "British-controlled waterway connecting the Mediterranean and Red Seas, an essential target in North Africa.",
          "answer": "Suez Canal"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country that sent the Afrika Korps to fight in North Africa but was forced to retreat to allied Italy.",
          "answer": "Nazi Germany"
        },
        {
          "question": "Commander of the Afrika Korps who gained the nickname “Desert Fox” for his success in Africa.",
          "answer": "Erwin Rommel"
        },
        {
          "question": "Final British commander in North Africa. His Eighth Army won the Battle of El Alamein.",
          "answer": "Bernard Law Montgomery"
        },
        {
          "question": "British island with capital Valetta where submarines and airplanes targeted enemy shipping in the Mediterranean.",
          "answer": "Malta"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mediterranean island targeted by Operation Husky, which was launched from North Africa.",
          "answer": "Sicily"
        },
        {
          "question": "Operation name for the Anglo-American invasion of North Africa, which landed in French-held territory in November 1942.",
          "answer": [
            "Operation Torch",
            "Operation Gymnast"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Vital harbor lost by the British after the Battle of Gazala. Its defenders became known as the Desert Rats.",
          "answer": "Tobruk"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The first Boeing 747 to suffer an accident was this airline’s Flight 540 in 1974; 55 people died in Kenya in its worst disaster. In 1977, one of this airline’s planes was stormed by members of GSG 9, ending a hostage crisis by Palestinian hijackers who wanted the release of members of the Red Army (20 pts)",
        "Faction. In 1972, another of this airline’s planes was hijacked, leading to the release of three members of Black September who committed the Munich massacre. (10 pts)",
        "Cologne serves as headquarters for, for ten points, what largest German airline?"
      ],
      "answer": "Deutsche Lufthansa AG"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This artist designed stained glass in memory of Dag Hammerskj¨old for the United Nations Headquarters dedicated to Peace. He used a Cubist style to show a (20 pts)",
        "purple-coated violinist standing on top of two houses, based off his childhood in a Hasidic community. At the top of one painting, he included a woman playing the violin upside-down and a (10 pts)",
        "green-skinned man holding a glowing tree while facing a farm animal. For ten points, name this Russian painter of I and the Village."
      ],
      "answer": "Marc Chagall"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This event’s perpetrator was aided by Lori Fortier, who helped forge a fake driver’s license. This event prompted Bob Dole to pass the Effective Death Penalty Act. A Pulitzer Prize was given to Charles Porter for his photograph of (20 pts)",
        "firefighter Chris Fields carrying a baby wounded in this event. This attack was allegedly motivated by federal actions at Ruby Ridge and Waco, and was carried out via a (10 pts)",
        "bomb strapped to a rental Ryder truck. For ten points, name this 1995 attack upon the Alfred P. Murrah building, carried out by Timothy McVeigh in an American state capital."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Oklahoma City bombing",
        "broad equivalents for bombing, like “attack,” after “bomb” has been read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This work informs listeners that “they shall be left to fall as they are inclined by their own weight” when discussing a passage that notes “Their foot shall slide in due time” from Deuteronomy. The image of a (20 pts)",
        "spider dangling over a pit of fire is invoked in this work, which warned listeners that “there is nothing that keeps wicked men [...] out of (10 pts)",
        "hell, but the mere pleasure of God.” For ten points, name this fearsome sermon, a powerful example of the first Great Awakening, delivered in 1741 by Jonathan Edwards."
      ],
      "answer": "Sinners in the Hands of an Angry God"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) States in this era were grouped into Vertical or Horizontal alliances based on their stance towards the most powerful state. A flourishing of philosophy called the Hundred (20 pts)",
        "Schools of Thought ended with this period. It began after the breakup of the Jin state and occurred during the Eastern Zhou period. This period came after a time of smaller states known as the (10 pts)",
        "Spring and Autumn Period. The great works of Confucianism were compiled during, for ten points, what period of Chinese history that ended when Qin Shi Huangdi unified China?"
      ],
      "answer": "Warring States Period"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Johannes Ockeghem wrote the first surviving polyphonic example of this composition. Berlioz wrote one of these pieces with four brass bands to commemorate the July Revolution. These pieces normally feature a (20 pts)",
        "hymn attributed to Thomas of Celano. Another of these pieces includes a trombone solo in its “Tuba Mirum” section and was completed by Franz (10 pts)",
        "Sussmayr after its composer died while working on its “Lacrimosa.” A “Dies Irae” is usually found in, for ten points, what type of composition that was Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart’s last, a mass for the dead?"
      ],
      "answer": "requiems or requiem mass"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After this man’s citizen militia fled, the Spanish sacked the city of Prato in 1512, ending the rule of Piero Soderini. This man wrote that “because Fortune is a (20 pts)",
        "woman, one must thrash her to have one’s way with her,” and he discussed the first 10 books of the History of Rome in his Discourses on Livy. Another work by this author views Cesare Borgia as a model (10 pts)",
        "ruler, claims that it is better to be feared than to be loved. and was dedicated to Lorenzo d’Medici. For ten points, name this Italian author of The Prince."
      ],
      "answer": "Niccol´o Machiavelli"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man and William Pinkney produced a never-ratified agreement to extend Jay’s Treaty. This man provoked a controversy by allowing Andrew Jackson to cross international borders during the (20 pts)",
        "Seminole War. William Plumer voted for Richard Rush and John Quincy Adams instead of Daniel Tompkins and this man, becoming the only (10 pts)",
        "elector to vote against him in 1820. The Era of Good Feelings was led by, for ten points, what President who protected Latin America from European interference with a famous doctrine?"
      ],
      "answer": "James Monroe"
    }
  ]
}